A Guide to the Virginia Conservartion Commission, Art Index Project Files, 1870-1961
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Conservation Commission, Art Index Project Files, 1870-1961
Library of Virginia
37190
1.75 cubic feet
Transferred from the Virginia Fine Arts Museum, 9 March 2000.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Virginia Fine Arts Museum, 9 March 2000.
Historical Information
The Art Index Project was formed on January 12, 1937 when a citizens committee including Mr. Wilbur Hall, (Virginia State Librarian) convinced Governor George C. Peery of the importance of documenting Virginia's artistic heritage. The Art Index Project was for a limited term of 18 months with Miss Julia Sully as Director beginning on March 1, 1937. The 18-month trial term was to establish whether or not there was sufficient interest in the documentation and preservation of Virginia's historic and artistic culture. Miss Sully's salary was paid by private donations while her office and supplies were furnished by the state.
In May of 1938 Governor James Price was more than satisfied with the work that was being undertaken and authorized the Art Index Project to continue its work within the Virginia Conservation Commission. According to Miss Sully's summary notes the 1940 Legislative Session budget authorization resulted in the Virginia Art Index Projects movement to the "Department of History and Archaeology" which took place on July 1, 1940. Miss Sully's working title became Junior Historian 1. She continued her work with the Project until January 1942, the date of her last monthly report. Her interest in Virginia historic endeavors continued throughout the years.
The Art Index Project was originally part of the State Commission on Conservation and Development(originally created in 1929) and then the Virginia Conservation Commission created in 1938. The Art Index Project was moved to the Division of History and Archaeology originally created in 1929 within the State Commission on Conservation and Development. The Virginia Conservation Commission eventually evolved into the Dept of Conservation and Development. The final incarnation of legislatively mandated name changes and reorganizations occurred on March 27, 1989 with the creation of the Dept of Historic Resources. The Art Index Project officially ceased operations in January of 1942.
Scope and Content Information
The Julia Sully Subject files document the activities of Miss Julia Sully while serving as director of the Art Index Division. The records include personal family photographs and documentation of various forms of artistic work that emphasize a connection to the people of the Commonwealth. There are samples of family correspondence, postcards received and examples of American and English artistic paintings. The records include monthly reports, photographic samples of artwork and a general statement of purpose for the Art Index Division.
The Newsclippings series includes articles written by Miss Sully and others documenting the cultural interests and activities within the state. The clippings are photocopies from VPA news clip bureau as well as newspapers from throughout the state. Some of the Virginia newspapers featuring articles include the Richmond Times Dispatch, Richmond News Leader, Roanoke Times and the Norfolk Virginian Pilot. There is also a "scrapbook" maintained by Miss Sully of news articles that she authored prior to and while working for the Art Index Project.
Arrangement
Organized into two (2) series: Series I. Julia Sully Subject Files, c. 1870-1955 (Bulk dates 1933-1942); Series II. Newsclippings, 1929-1961.
Contents List
- Series I. Julia Sully Subject Files, 1870-1955
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - American Federation of Arts-Art Newsletter, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles by Julia Sully, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Background Material for Indexing Project, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cincinnati Modern Art Society, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Commentary on News Article, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (transcription of family letters), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - DeSaint-Memin, Feverant the work of, 1934-1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Evans, Grose-The Province and Grammar of Visual Art, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Furniture of the Old South-Exhibit Captions, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Furniture of the Old South-Photographs, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General Summary and Report Notes, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - H.P. Cook Studio Sketch, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Judge the Jury Exhibition, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Monthly Reports-Virginia Art Index Division, 1937-1942 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Orozco, Jose Clemente and Rivera, Diego, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - P (Miscellaneous), 1937-1943 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Painter's Modern, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Painter's Richmond, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Painting-American and English, 1935-1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Painting-Foreign, 1922-1935 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Painting-Primitive/Sculptors, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Payne, John, Barton, 1926-1936 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Petersburg, Virginia, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Peticolas, Edward, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Photographs-American File, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Portraits-American, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Plan for Summary of Art Index Project, 1938-1942 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Planning Your Town-Exhibition, 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Pocahontas, 1910-1939 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Pollia, Joseph, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Portraits-Foreign, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Postcards Received, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Pottery, 1935-1939 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Prints, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Questionnaires (Blank Forms), 1942 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Quiz Kids, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Randolph Family, 1934-1941 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Reynolds, Joshua, Sir., 1939-1942 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Richmond-Newsclippings, 1935-1942 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Ryder, Albert P., 1936 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - S, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Seibel, Fred O., 1944 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Schools, 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Shelley, Byron, Portrait?, 1935-1939 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Sheppard, W.L., 1939 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Silhouettes, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Silver and other Metals, 1935-1938 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Silver in Virginia Churches, 1935-1948 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Silvette, Miss, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Smibert, John, (Notes on), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Smith, John, Capitan, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Smyth, Jeanne, Sully., 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Statues, 1935-1939 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Sully Family History, 1903-1904 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Sully Family Photographs, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Sully, Julia, Biography, 1936-1943 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sully, Julia, Notebook, 1920-1951 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Sully, Julia, Photographs, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Sully, Julia, Photographs and Negatives, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sully, Julia, Portraits and Family Members, 1870-1900 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Sully, Thomas, 1939-1941 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Sully, Thomas, Newsclippings, 1922-1939 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Virginia, 1936-1940 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Series II. Newsclippings, 1929-1961
  Arranged chronologically by newsclipping date.
  - VPA News Clip Bureau, 1940-1946 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - VPA News Clip Bureau, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - VPA News Clip Bureau, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - VPA News Clip Bureau, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - VPA News Clip Bureau, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - VPA News Clip Bureau, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - VPA News Clip Bureau, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - VPA News Clip Bureau, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - VPA News Clip Bureau, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Richmond Times Dispatch Centennial Edition Newsclippings, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Richmond Times Dispatch Clippings, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Richmond Times Dispatch Clippings, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Richmond Times Dispatch Clippings, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Richmond Times Dispatch Clippings, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Richmond Times Dispatch Clippings, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Richmond Times Dispatch Clippings, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Richmond Times Dispatch, Richmond News Leader, Roanoke Times, Roanoke World News, Portsmouth Star, and Norfolk Virginian Pilot, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Richmond Times Dispatch, Richmond News Leader, Alexandria Gazette and Evening Leader, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Richmond Times Dispatch, Richmond News Leader, Virginia Highway Bulletin, Roanoke Times and World News, 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Richmond Times Dispatch News Articles on Cities and Towns in Virginia-Alta Vista to Colonial Beach, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Richmond Times Dispatch News Articles on Cities and Towns in Virginia-Colonial Heights to Franklin, 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Richmond Times Dispatch News Articles on Cities and Towns in Virginia-Fredericksburg to Montross, 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Richmond Times Dispatch News Articles on Cities and Towns in Virginia-Orange to Yorktown, 1950-19+51 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Newsclippings about Furniture of the Old South, 1951-1952 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Newsclippings Habiliments of Heroines Virginia Museum of Fine Arts Exhibit, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook of Julia Sully News Articles (xerox copies), 1929-1941 (Box 5, Folder 9)